Department of Music Records, 1918-2001
Smith College Archives
Department of Music Records
1918-[ongoing]
Smith College. Dept. of Music.
RG 52 UUID:6240785a-c7fb-450e-b35a-5a8fcc6cdd76
10 boxes (14 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Records contain information regarding the history of the program, booklets, course information, department minutes, office files, faculty files, Smith College concerts and recitals and the New Valley Music Press, the only university press in the country devoted to the publication of modern American music.
Music Department at Smith College:
When Smith College opened in 1875 the study of music was conducted in a conservatory located in Pierce Hall, adjacent to College Hall. There, professors George W. Steele and J. Wells Champney instructed the students three times per week. From 1877 to 1879 a school of music was organized due to high demand from students wishing to study. The demand was so high that the conservatory soon became too small and inadequate for the number of students, and in 1880 the bowling alley in the gymnasium was converted into music rooms and the first story of the building was given up entirely to the music program. With demand for music instruction ever-increasing, the Executive Committee secured plans for a new building which was opened during the 1882-1883 college year. At that time, Smith College was believed by many to be the finest music school in the country. In 1903, Music became a department of the college, while the study of performance for credit continued to be offered within a liberal arts program, which was unusual for colleges at that time. In 1924 the Music Department moved to the newly constructed Sage Hall, and in 1968 the neighboring Werner Josten Library of the Performing Arts was built to house one of the finest undergraduate music libraries in the country. Extensive renovations to Sage Hall in 1989-90 resulted in the construction of Earle Recital Hall and the reconfiguration of the main auditorium, re-christened Sweeney Concert Hall, into an acoustically ideal hall for performances ranging from solo recitals to small orchestral concerts. Sweeney Concert Hall is the venue for the department's acclaimed concert series. The department's facilities include numerous practice rooms with grand pianos, an electro-acoustic music studio, and a digital classroom equipped with state-of-the-art computer workstations. Student participation outside of the classroom was equally important. Department clubs were formed as early as 1880, when the first Glee Club was formed and disbanded the same year and later re-formed in 1888. Since 1880 musical clubs have had a presence in the Smith community: the Noteables, Chamber Singers, the All-Smith Choir, Class Choirs, the Smith College Oratorio Chorus, Chamber Orchestra, String Orchestra Symphony Orchestra, the Smith-Amherst Orchestra, the training Orchestra and the Smiffenpoofs. Concerts and recitals have been held from 1876 to the present.
The Valley Music Press:
The Valley Music Press was established in 1942 by Ross Lee Finney, then a faculty member at Smith College, and John Verral. For a number of years Verral was based at Mount Holyoke College as part of the music departments of Smith College and Mt. Holyoke College and was supported by these two institutions. The Valley Music Press was unique because it was the only university press in the country devoted to the publication of modern American music. It was a non-profit organization for the distribution at moderate price of music by contemporary composers. Works were chosen as being practical for performance, rewarding for study, and varied both in medium and in place in the contemporary scene. As of 1962, the press had 55 publications on hand. Needless to say, the business details were many and varied. Meetings of the Executive Committee were held during the year to discuss new music to be published. It was felt that the time had come for the Press to become a member of the Smith College publications, and that it would be necessary to sever its connection with Mount Holyoke College. President Mendenhall gave his support to this goal, and also arranged for the sum of $400.00 annually to be provided by Smith College towards operating expenses of the Press. (Formerly, $200.00 came from the Music Department at Smith College and $200.00 from Mount Holyoke College.) It was also agreed that the name would be changed to signify the end of the original partnership. Hence, the Press was renamed the New Valley Music Press (NVMP) of Smith College. The NVMP ceased publication in December of 1996.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
Access is open, without restriction.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
History of the Collection
These records were transferred to the College Archives in the Summer of 2002.
Search Terms
Smith College. Dept. of Music.; Smith College--History--Sources.; New Valley Music Press--History--Sources.; Music--Instruction and study--Massachusetts--Northampton.; New Valley Music Press.
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional Music Department records are also located in the College Archives. Information about clubs, concerts and recitals, course and faculty information can be found at 52. Academic Departments: Music and at 42. Faculty Biographical Files. Please contact the College Archives shelf list for information about these records. Photographs and general information about the various buildings that housed the Music Department and Library are available in 22. Buildings and Grounds.
- DEPARTMENT MINUTES
  - Minutes 1918-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-66)
- OFFICE FILES
  - Operating budget 1997-98 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Sabbatical procedures 1997-98 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Presidential Fellowships, released time and replacement staffing 1997-99 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Deans suggestions for chairs 1997-98 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Information regarding faculty offices and computers undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Appointments to the faculty:
    - Tenure-track positions undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Part-time, not on tenure-track undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Proposal for new academic offerings undated (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - General guidelines undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Leaflets 1957-1973 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Inventory: Archives Bound Volumes 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Music book associates 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Mailing list archives 1959 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Exchanges and gifts: special correspondence 1956-1970 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Copyrights 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Standing order file 1960-1977 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Sage Hall rededication ceremony 1991 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - 8 books of Selected List of Choruses for Women's Voices (2 copies) 1927, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Naegele, Phillipp Otto - lecture (2 copies) 1983 (Box 2)
- FACULTY FILES (alphabetical)
  - Accompanists (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Accompanists (LaSalle) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Allison, Lucille Aubade (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ankudowich - Werner Josten Music Library (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ard, Jamee (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Auerswald, Adrienne (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bezanson, Philip (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Boatwright, Howard (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Boykan, Martin (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Brunswick, Mark (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Brunswick, Mark: Viola Solo (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Burt, George (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Callaway, Ann (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Carter, Elliot: Song, Voyage (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chernin, Mallorie (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - DeFelice, Elizabeth (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Degenring, Eloise: Finardi (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Donovan, Richard (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Douma, Jeffrey: letter of appointment (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Duke, John: Two Songs (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Dushkin, Dorothy (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Elwell, Herbert (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Etler Alvin: Quartet and Sonata (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Evans, Paul (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Fankhauser, James (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Fennelly, Brian (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Finney, Ross Lee (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Flight, Paul M. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Flutists Pro Rata: Four Songs (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Goldman, Lisa (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Gotwals, Vernon (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Graduate Students: Teaching Fellows (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Greenbaum, Adrianne (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Harsh, Tamara (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Hayes, Gregory (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Hoag, Charles (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Holden, David (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Hunter, Ann (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Imbrie, Andrew: Piano Sonata (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
  - Jacobi, Frederick (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Hunter, Johnson: Serenade (Box 2, Folder 47-48)
  - Josten, Werner (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Kadlubkiewicz, Veronica (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Kanitz, Dr. Ernest (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Kanitz, Ernest: Notturno (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Kelly, Thomas (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Kennedy Professor: Howard Brown (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Koch, John (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Kolb, G. Robert (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
  - Sue, Kurian (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lamb, Hubert: Publication Project (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Laufer, Edward: Variations for seven instruments (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - London, Edwin (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Malek, Eugene (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - McAllister, Suzanne (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - McIntyre, Ken (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Miller, Robert (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Montgomery, Anna (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Morrison, Theodore: Application for the position of Director of Choral Activities (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
  - Murray, Jessel (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Naegele, Philip (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Noble, Clifton (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ramos-Santana, Jose (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rosenberg, Joel (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Shansky, Marjorie (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Skarimbas, Carol Bergey (voice) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Solomon, Magen (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Stafford, Elaine (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Stahl, Dorothy (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Sussman, Lynn and Michael (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Tarlow, Karen (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Thayer, Lucinda (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Theorist X (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Usher, Leslie (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - van der Loo, Marion (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - VanBuskirk, John (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Vitali, G. B.: Volume XIV (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Voice search: Voice appointment (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
  - Waites, Althea: (Box 3, Folder 35-37)
    RESTRICTED until 2049, located on Level B
  - Wallfisch, Lory (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Wells, Kathryn (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Wheelock, Gretchen (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Wilsen, Carlotta (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ziarko, John (Box 3, Folder 42)
- FACULTY FILES (course materials)
  - Caccini, La Liberazione di Ruggiero d'all' Isola d' Alcina - Volume 7 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Smith College Music Archives - Tartini Concerti Volume 9 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Archives - Volume 10 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Volume XI - Steffani (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Music Archives, Volume XII, Vitali, Concerto di Sonate Opus 4, edited by Doris Silbert, Gertrude Parker Smith and Louise Rood (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Volume XII - Errata (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Volume XIII (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Volume XV - Brahms Folk Songs (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Publicity cards - Choruses for Women's Voices (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Three Compositions for Piano, Copyright notice (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Original MSS - Music Department Archives (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Archives - Early history - original letters 1934-38 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Agents (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Archives I, II and III, requests for copies (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Twelve Sonatas for Violin and Piano by Geminiani Volume I (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - J.J. Fux - Costanza E Fortezza - Volume II (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Boccherini - Volume III (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Boccherini - second printing (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Canzoni, Sonetti e Frottole, edited by Dr. Einstein Volume IV (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Complimentary copies (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Advertising (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Financial arrangements - budget (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - General correspondence (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Boonin (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - de Rore, Cypriano (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Locke, Arthur (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Nowack, Lionel (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Palmer, Robert (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Panetti (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Porter, Quincy (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Riley (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Savioni (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Schickele, Peter (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Shepherd (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Stewart, David (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Tarlow, Karen (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
  - Verall, John (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Walker, George (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Weigel, Eugene (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Wheelock (Box 4, Folder 42)
- FACULTY FILES (departmental materials)
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Evaluation procedures (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Electronic Music Studio (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Senior evaluations 1977 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Clara Schumann Collection (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - 1963 Board of Counselors 1963 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Choral Direstor search 1980-81 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Choral position 83/86/87-88 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Catalogue copy (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Master calendar 1981-82 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Catalogue 1984-85 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Copier (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Commencement Concert 1981-82 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Black Musicians 1979 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Boston Pops (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Chair 1984 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Agenda 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Advisory committee 1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Arcadelt - Volume 2 - Everett Helm (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Caccini (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Statistics, financial statement, yearly sales card file (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Catalogues (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Unpaid orders (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Standing orders 1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Selected list 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Advertising list (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Requisition for selected list 1964-67 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Practical Music fees (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Vespers - Christmas Vespers tickets (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Theory (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Teaching Fellow (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Smith-Amherst Orchestra - Up to 1975 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Security for Sage Hall (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Presser Foundation (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Philosophical discussions (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Odds and ends (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Lecture Committee (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Josten Library Issue (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Governance Committee (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Five Colleges
    - Orchestra (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Music Planning Committee (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Chairs (Box 5, Folder 27-29)
    - Early Music Committee: Evaluation report (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
- SMITH COLLEGE CONCERTS AND RECITALS
  - Bound Programs 1937-1957 (Box 6)
  - Bound Programs 1957-1971 (Box 7)
  - Bound Programs 1971-77 (Box 8)
  - Programs (loose)
    - 1995-96 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1997-98 (Box 8, Folder 2-7)
    - 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 8-16)
- NEW VALLEY MUSIC PRESS
  - History 1962 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Constitution 1962 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Purchase orders 1986-87 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Meetings 1952-54 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - United States Information Service 1961-62 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation 1962-64 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Advertising rates 1986 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Requisitions 1973-1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Announcements, notices and reviews 1951-1974 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - News releases 1963 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Article: Louise Rood 1956 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - New Fund 1977 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Composer royalty sheets undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - New set-up 1966 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Financial reports 1946-1984 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Alvin Etler Memorial Competition 1973-77 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Accounts to be posted 1988 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Alphacomp 1988-89 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Check receipts 1985-88 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Copyright forms undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Copyright 1988 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Catalogue 1992 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence 1991-96 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Complete 1993-2000 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Copyright and fair use: Compositions for Piano 1992 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Teal binder: Office ledgers 1949-1991 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Press correspondence 1970-1991 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Composer's refunds 1953, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Price listing undated (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Bezanson, Philip - Diversion for Brass Trio (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Baotwright, Howard - Trio (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Boykan, Martin - String Quartet (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Brunswick, Mark - Viola Solo (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Burt, George (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Ann Callaway - Four Elements for Horn and Piano (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Donovan, Richard
    - Four Songs (Box 9, Folder 28-34)
    - Terzetto (Box 9)
    - Quartet for Woodwinds (Box 9)
      - and Clarinet in B flat (Box 9)
      - and Bassoon (Box 9)
      - and Oboe (Box 9)
      - and Flute (Box 9)
  - Duke, John
    - My Soul (Box 9, Folder 35-38)
    - End of World (Box 9)
    - Viola Alone (Box 9)
    - Three Poems by Mark Van Doren (Box 9)
  - Dushkin, Dorothy - Quintet (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Elliott, Carter - Voyage (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Elwell, Herbert
    - Agamede's Song (Box 9, Folder 41-42)
    - Suffolk Owl (Box 9)
  - Etler, Alvin
    - Morning Glory (Box 9, Folder 43-45)
    - Duo (Box 9)
    - Quartet for Oboe, Clarinet, Viola and Bassoon (Box 9)
  - Finney, Ross Lee
    - Vi and Piano Third Sonata (Box 9, Folder 46-52)
    - Piano Sonata (Box 9)
    - Slow Piece (Box 9)
    - Three Love Songs (Box 9)
    - Three 17th Century Lyrics (Box 9)
    - 7th and 8th String Quartets (Box 9)
    - 2nd Sonata in C - Cello (Box 9)
  - Galieli, Vincenzo - Volume VIII (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Gogarty - To a Trout (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Golden Stockings (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Hamm, Charles (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Hoag, Charles (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Holden, David (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Hunter, Johnson - Serenade (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Imbrie, Andrew - Sonata for Piano (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Jacobi, Frederick
    - Odyssey (Box 9, Folder 61-62)
    - Three Songs (Box 9)
  - Josten, Werner (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Kanitz, Ernest - Notturno for Flute, Violin and Viola (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Koch, John - Elegy (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Lamb, Hubert - Toccata (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Laufer, Edward - Variations for Seven Instruments (Box 9)
  - London, Edwin
    - Soantina for Viola and Piano (Box 9, Folder 67-68)
    - Third Day (Box 9)
  - Luening
    - Three Duets for Two Flutes (Box 9, Folder 69-74)
    - Third Short Sonata (Box 9)
    - Second Short Sonata (Box 9)
    - Sonatina (Box 9)
    - Sonata composed in two dayturnes (Box 9)
    - Andante and variations (Box 9)
  - Nobel, Clifton Jr. - Songs of Innocence and Experience (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Nowak, Lionel - Diptych (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Panetti (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Porter, Quincy
    - Divertimento (Box 10, Folder 4-11)
    - Duo (Box 10)
    - Little Trio (Box 10)
    - Poem (Box 10)
    - String Quartet Number 5 (Box 10)
    - String Quartet Number 7 (Box 10)
    - String Quartet Number 8 (Box 10)
    - Speed Etude (Box 10)
  - Reverie (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Riley, John - String Quartet Number 2 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Schickele, Peter - After Spring Sunset (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Serenade (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Shepherd, Arthur
    - Seven Songs (Box 10, Folder 16-18)
    - Star Lake (Box 10)
    - Fiddlers (Box 10)
  - Smith, Melville (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Spinning Song (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Spratlan, Lewis
    - Images (Box 10, Folder 21-22)
    - Images for Soprano and Piano (Box 10)
  - Stern, Robert - A Little Bit of Music (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Steuermann
    - Background pieces (Box 10, Folder 24-26)
    - Improvisation and Allegro (Box 10)
    - Three Songs (Box 10)
  - Stewart - Spectral Dance (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Tarlow
    - Seven Sabbath Songs (Box 10, Folder 28-29)
    - Renascence (Box 10)
  - Verrall, John
    - String Trio (Box 10, Folder 30-32)
    - Autumn Sketches (Box 10)
    - String Quartet (Box 10)
  - Virgil (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Vitali - Volume XIV (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Walker, George (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Weigel, Eugene - Four Songs (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Weigel, John - Sonata for Strings (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Wheelock - Sonata for Solo Flute (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Notebook: Items of interest (Box 10)